[
    {
        "question": "Israel approved a $11.13 million plan to expand settlements in the ___________, citing border security concerns after Syria's Assad regime's fall.",
        "options": [
            "West Bank",
            "Gaza Strip",
            "Golan Heights",
            "Jerusalem",
            "Syria"
        ],
        "answer": "Golan Heights"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state was awarded the Geographical Indication (GI) tag for its traditional handicraft, 'Gharchola,' known for its intricate designs and cultural motifs?",
        "options": [
            "Rajasthan",
            "Gujarat",
            "Punjab",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Haryana"
        ],
        "answer": "Gujarat"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which prestigious award has Indian environmentalist Madhav Gadgil received in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Nobel Prize for Environmental Science",
            "UNEP's Lifetime Achievement Award",
            "Tyler Prize for Environmental Achievement",
            "Padma Bhushan",
            "Environment Engineer Award"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is set to introduce the Banking Laws (Amendment) Bill, 2024 in the Lok Sabha?",
        "options": [
            "Narendra Modi",
            "Nirmala Sitharaman",
            "Amit Shah",
            "Shaktikanta Das",
            "Pankaj Chaudhary"
        ],
        "answer": "Nirmala Sitharaman"
    },
    {
        "question": "What new facility has the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) enabled for Small Finance Banks?",
        "options": [
            "Offering loans without collateral",
            "Offering insurance services",
            "Enabling foreign currency exchange",
            "Providing micro-investment options",
            "Offering pre-sanctioned credit via UPI"
        ],
        "answer": "Offering pre-sanctioned credit via UPI"
    },
    {
        "question": "What initiative has the Reserve Bank of India (RBI), led by Governor Shaktikanta Das, announced to enhance public communication and financial literacy?",
        "options": [
            "Launch of a new mobile app",
            "Launch of a podcast series",
            "Organizing national seminars",
            "Launch of an online financial literacy course",
            "Introduction of financial literacy campaigns in schools"
        ],
        "answer": "Launch of a podcast series"
    },
    {
        "question": "What significant milestone has SBI Card recently achieved?",
        "options": [
            "Surpassing 15 million credit cards in circulation",
            "Surpassing 20 million credit cards in circulation",
            "Entering the international credit card market",
            "Reaching 10 million active users",
            "Launching its 100th credit card variant"
        ],
        "answer": "Surpassing 20 million credit cards in circulation"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main goal of the partnership between Mahindra Finance and Magma HDI General Insurance?",
        "options": [
            "To introduce new insurance products",
            "To expand financial access for emerging India",
            "To enhance digital payment solutions",
            "To offer co-branded credit cards",
            "To promote investment in agriculture"
        ],
        "answer": "To expand financial access for emerging India"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much does Bank of India (BoI) plan to raise through the issuance of infrastructure bonds?",
        "options": [
            "₹3,000 crore",
            "₹4,000 crore",
            "₹6,000 crore",
            "₹7,000 crore",
            "₹5,000 crore"
        ],
        "answer": "₹5,000 crore"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two companies have ended their co-branded credit cards partnership?",
        "options": [
            "ICICI Bank and HDFC Bank",
            "RBL Bank and Bajaj Finance",
            "Axis Bank and Kotak Mahindra Bank",
            "SBI and HDFC Bank",
            "IDFC Bank and Yes Bank"
        ],
        "answer": "RBL Bank and Bajaj Finance"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company has had the restrictions imposed by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) lifted, led by Sachin Bansal?",
        "options": [
            "Paytm",
            "Navi Finserv",
            "Lendingkart",
            "Bajaj Finserv",
            "Finbox"
        ],
        "answer": "Navi Finserv"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much has India contributed to the BRICS New Development Bank (NDB), and how much has been loaned for externally aided projects in areas like transportation?",
        "options": [
            "$1 billion; $3,528 million",
            "$1.5 billion; $4,074 million",
            "$2 billion; $4,867 million",
            "$2.5 billion; $5,575 million",
            "$3 billion; $6,500 million"
        ],
        "answer": "$2 billion; $4,867 million"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the purpose of the nation-wide drive launched by State Bank of India (SBI)?",
        "options": [
            "To promote digital banking",
            "To raise awareness about inoperative account activation",
            "To offer new banking services",
            "To encourage saving habits",
            "To introduce new loan schemes"
        ],
        "answer": "To raise awareness about inoperative account activation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization has Razorpay collaborated with to enhance the security of India's digital payments ecosystem?",
        "options": [
            "Reserve Bank of India",
            "Ministry of Home Affairs",
            "Indian Cyber Crime Coordination Centre",
            "Both b and c",
            "National Payments Corporation of India"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the growth rate of bank credit to NBFCs in October 2024 compared to the same period last year?",
        "options": [
            "10.2%",
            "12.5%",
            "6.4%",
            "8.0%",
            "18.3%"
        ],
        "answer": "6.4%"
    },
    {
        "question": "As of October 31, 2024, how many accounts have been opened under the Mahila Samman Savings Certificate Scheme?",
        "options": [
            "30.50 lakh",
            "35.20 lakh",
            "40.30 lakh",
            "43.30 lakh",
            "45.70 lakh"
        ],
        "answer": "43.30 lakh"
    },
    {
        "question": "With which general insurance company has Mahindra Finance signed a strategic corporate agency agreement?",
        "options": [
            "ICICI Lombard General Insurance",
            "Magma HDI General Insurance",
            "Bajaj Allianz General Insurance",
            "HDFC ERGO General Insurance",
            "Reliance General Insurance"
        ],
        "answer": "Magma HDI General Insurance"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which mutual fund company launched the Quant Fund, an open-ended equity scheme based on a quant-based investing approach?",
        "options": [
            "HDFC Mutual Fund",
            "ICICI Prudential Mutual Fund",
            "SBI Mutual Fund",
            "Kotak Mahindra Mutual Fund",
            "Axis Mutual Fund"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is India’s total external debt in 2023, as per the World Bank International Debt Report?",
        "options": [
            "$610.67 billion",
            "$635.84 billion",
            "$646.79 billion",
            "$655.74 billion",
            "$675.95 billion"
        ],
        "answer": "$646.79 billion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has launched the Pragati Savings Account to cater to the banking needs of rural and semi-urban residents in India?",
        "options": [
            "SBI",
            "ICICI Bank",
            "HDFC Bank",
            "Axis Bank",
            "Bank of Baroda"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country has approved a possible $1.17 billion deal to sell India support equipment for MH-60R multi-role helicopters under its Foreign Military Sales programme?",
        "options": [
            "USA",
            "Russia",
            "France",
            "China",
            "Australia"
        ],
        "answer": "USA"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which rocket was used by the Indian Space Research Organization (ISRO) to launch the European Space Agency’s Probe 3 spacecraft?",
        "options": [
            "PSLV- C 54",
            "PSLV-C59",
            "PSLV-C58",
            "PSLV-C57",
            "PSLV-C56"
        ],
        "answer": "PSLV-C59"
    },
    {
        "question": "In December 2024, what is the name of the unmanned surface vessel handed over by GRSE to DRDO?",
        "options": [
            "Jalveer",
            "Jaldoot",
            "Jalrakshak",
            "Jalpari",
            "Jalvahan"
        ],
        "answer": "Jaldoot"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Russian-built multi-role stealth-guided missile frigate INS Tushil was commissioned into the Indian Navy at the Yantar Shipyard in Kaliningrad, Russia. What is unique about the construction of INS Tushil?",
        "options": [
            "It is the first Indian-built stealth frigate.",
            "It is the seventh ship of Project 1135.6, built under an India-Russia collaboration.",
            "It is a nuclear-powered frigate built by Baltiysky Zawod.",
            "It is the first ship constructed under the Atmanirbhar Bharat initiative.",
            "It is the first ship to feature entirely indigenous weaponry."
        ],
        "answer": "It is the seventh ship of Project 1135.6, built under an India-Russia collaboration."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which team has won the 11th ACC U19 Men’s Asia Cup Final in Dubai?",
        "options": [
            "Bangladesh",
            "India",
            "Pakistan",
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Afghanistan"
        ],
        "answer": "Bangladesh"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has won the BWF Super 100 Guwahati Masters 2024 badminton singles title?",
        "options": [
            "Sathish Karunakaran",
            "Kidambi Srikanth",
            "Lakshya Sen",
            "Prannoy H.S.",
            "Chirag Shetty"
        ],
        "answer": "Sathish Karunakaran"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which countries will jointly host the 2030 FIFA World Cup?",
        "options": [
            "Spain, Portugal, and Morocco",
            "Saudi Arabia, Morocco, and Argentina",
            "Spain, France, and Italy",
            "Portugal, Argentina, and Brazil",
            "Saudi Arabia, Portugal, and Morocco"
        ],
        "answer": "Spain, Portugal, and Morocco"
    },
    {
        "question": "The 2027 Women’s World Cup in Brazil will be played from June 24 to July 25, FIFA, soccer’s international governing body announced. How many teams will participate in the 2027 Women’s World Cup?",
        "options": [
            "16",
            "24",
            "28",
            "32",
            "36"
        ],
        "answer": "32"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has won the Formula One Abu Dhabi Grand Prix 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Carlos Sainz",
            "Charles Leclerc",
            "Lewis Hamilton",
            "George Russell",
            "Lando Norris"
        ],
        "answer": "5"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company has secured ₹136-crore contract to supply indigenously designed High Mobility Vehicles (HMVs) 8×8?",
        "options": [
            "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited",
            "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited",
            "BEML Limited",
            "Tata Advanced Systems",
            "Bharat Electronics Limited"
        ],
        "answer": "BEML Limited"
    },
    {
        "question": "In a significant step toward bolstering India’s defence capabilities and promoting the ‘Aatmanirbhar Bharat’ initiative, the Ministry of Defence (MoD) has signed a contract with Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd (HAL) for the procurement of 12 Su-30MKI aircraft. What is the percentage of homegrown content in the Su-30MKI aircraft being procured?",
        "options": [
            "50%",
            "55.2%",
            "60%",
            "62.6%",
            "75.6%"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new fielding coach for Mumbai Indians ahead of IPL 2025?",
        "options": [
            "James Pamment",
            "Carl Hopkinson",
            "Ravi Shastri",
            "Trevor Bayliss",
            "Mahela Jayawardene"
        ],
        "answer": "Carl Hopkinson"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which platform under Prasar Bharati will provide the live broadcast of the Hockey India League 2024-25?",
        "options": [
            "Doordarshan",
            "DD Sports",
            "DD National",
            "DD News",
            "Prasar Bharati TV"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who became the first woman cricketer to score four ODI centuries in a calendar year?",
        "options": [
            "Smriti Mandhana",
            "Mithali Raj",
            "Ellyse Perry",
            "Meg Lanning",
            "Harmanpreet Kaur"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has become the youngest bowler to take 100 wickets in all three formats of cricket?",
        "options": [
            "Shaheen Shah Afridi",
            "Jasprit Bumrah",
            "Pat Cummins",
            "Trent Boult",
            "Kagiso Rabada"
        ],
        "answer": "Shaheen Shah Afridi"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the women-exclusive bike taxi service launched by Uber in Bengaluru?",
        "options": [
            "Uber Bike Women",
            "Moto Women",
            "Uber She Rides",
            "Women Rider Connect",
            "Ride Women"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which famous lake in Maharashtra is being proposed for inclusion in the UNESCO World Heritage Sites list?",
        "options": [
            "Powai Lake",
            "Lonar Lake",
            "Shivaji Sagar Lake",
            "Tadoba Lake",
            "Rankala Lake"
        ],
        "answer": "Lonar Lake"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which date will Rajasthan observe Pravasi Rajasthani Diwas every year?",
        "options": [
            "15 August",
            "26 January",
            "10 December",
            "2 October",
            "5 June"
        ],
        "answer": "10 December"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Chief Minister launched the Mukhyamantri Paushtik Alpahar Yojana to provide nutritious snacks to students?",
        "options": [
            "Yogi Adityanath",
            "Bhupendrabhai Patel",
            "Ashok Gehlot",
            "Shivraj Singh Chouhan",
            "Naveen Patnaik"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which city set a Guinness World Record with 5,000 Acharyas reciting Gita verses?",
        "options": [
            "Varanasi",
            "Bhopal",
            "Haridwar",
            "Ujjain",
            "Ayodhya"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhopal"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the 10th World Ayurveda Congress and Arogya Expo inaugurated?",
        "options": [
            "Varanasi",
            "Dehradun",
            "Jaipur",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Lucknow"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rhino reintroduction efforts have gained momentum in which wildlife sanctuary in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Namdapha National Park",
            "Dibang Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Ering Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Mouling National Park",
            "Pakke Tiger Reserve"
        ],
        "answer": "Ering Wildlife Sanctuary"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization has partnered with HSBC to provide funding for trade transactions worth up to $1 billion, to bridge the funding gap for emerging market trade?",
        "options": [
            "International Monetary Fund",
            "World Trade Organization",
            "International Finance Corporation",
            "Asian Development Bank",
            "Both a and c"
        ],
        "answer": "International Finance Corporation"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the loan amount sanctioned by the Asian Development Bank (ADB) for Amaravati’s development?",
        "options": [
            "USD 500 million",
            "USD 788 million",
            "USD 900 million",
            "USD 718 million",
            "USD 850 million"
        ],
        "answer": "USD 788 million"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which General Insurance Company has collaborated with the Child Rights and You (CRY) organization to empower education for marginalized communities in Andhra Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Bajaj Allianz General Insurance",
            "Bharti AXA General Insurance",
            "Liberty General Insurance",
            "Go Digit General Insurance",
            "Universal Sompo General Insurance"
        ],
        "answer": "5"
    },
    {
        "question": "Canara Bank has launched a two-day nationwide Credit Outreach program to support the growth of Micro, Small, and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs). How many MSME clusters were covered by Canara Bank’s Nationwide Credit Outreach Program?",
        "options": [
            "150 clusters",
            "238 clusters",
            "300 clusters",
            "438 clusters",
            "508 clusters"
        ],
        "answer": "238 clusters"
    },
    {
        "question": "As of now ( Nov 24 ) , how many accounts have been opened under the Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana (PMJDY), and how many of them are inoperative?",
        "options": [
            "50.20 crore accounts opened, 12.50 crore inoperative",
            "54.03 crore accounts opened, 11.30 crore inoperative",
            "53.50 crore accounts opened, 10.80 crore inoperative",
            "55.00 crore accounts opened, 9.00 crore inoperative",
            "52.10 crore accounts opened, 13.00 crore inoperative"
        ],
        "answer": "54.03 crore accounts opened, 11.30 crore inoperative"
    },
    {
        "question": "HSBC India has launched HSBC Privé, an exclusive credit card. Who is this card specifically designed for?",
        "options": [
            "High Net-Worth Individuals (HNIs)",
            "Retail Banking Customers",
            "Global Private Banking Clients",
            "Corporate Employees",
            "Small Business Owners"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under which section of the SEBI Act, 1992, does the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) have the authority to protect investor interests and regulate the securities market?",
        "options": [
            "Section 10",
            "Section 11",
            "Section 12",
            "Section 15",
            "Section 20"
        ],
        "answer": "Section 11"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the initiative launched by Federal Bank to educate school children on life skills through traditional art forms?",
        "options": [
            "Kalakshethram",
            "Kaliyuum Karyavum",
            "Vidya Vaibhavam",
            "Kala Samvardhan",
            "Nurture & Inspire"
        ],
        "answer": "Kaliyuum Karyavum"
    }
]